Illinois Central Gulf Railroad Company Selected Personnel Files 5295
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Illinois Central Gulf Railroad Company Selected Personnel Files
1886-1973
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Illinois Central Gulf Railroad Company (ICG)
5295
22 cubic feet
22 linear ft.
Personnel records, records (documents).
Select records of the Personnel Department of the Illinois Central Gulf Railroad [ICRR]. The collection includes select personnel department files dealing with a wide range of subjects including railroad legislation, grievances, arbitration, wage and hour disputes, vacations, unionization efforts on the road, disciplinary issue, and discrimination against, harassment of, and racialized violence against black workers. Also found are historical documents about the ICRR, maps, correspondence files, minutes of meetings, transcripts of hearings before arbitration boards, interpretation of work rules, claims made by employees, and transcripts of legal proceedings.
3119392
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183> kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
E. Parker, January 28, 2012
EAD encoding:
Elizabeth Parker, December 07, 2017
Biographical / Historical
The Illinois Central Railroad [ICRR] was a Class I railroad in the central United States, connecting Chicago with both New Orleans, Louisiana and Mobile, Alabama on its main line.
The ICRR was formed in 1851 when the original investors succeeded in obtaining a large land grant from the federal government for the purpose of building a railroad under provisions granted by the Douglas Land Grant Bill. The grant was particularly generous, and the railroad expanded rapidly. The expansion was so rapid that the Illinois Central was one of the world's largest railroads by the time of the Civil War, branching out from Chicago westward to Sioux City, Iowa and southward to Cairo, Illinois. During the latter part of the nineteenth century and first two decades of the twentieth, the ICRR continued to add mileage to its holdings. This was especially the case in the south where the company succeeded in connecting Cairo with New Orleans. By the onset of the Great Depression, the Illinois Central controlled almost 5000 miles of track and was one of America's largest railroads.
As the twentieth century progressed, the ICRR, like the railroad industry in general, came under increasing pressure from new forms of transportation, especially the automobile. As a result, it began to experience shrinking profit margins and depressed markets for its services. The ICRR responded by implementing technologically advanced operating equipment, such as the diesel engine, cutting back on certain service, such as passenger service, and eliminating what it viewed as antiquated work practices among its employees.
This last aspect of the ICRR's response to its new operating environment produced acute struggles between the railroad unions and the railroad itself, culminating in the Presidential Emergency Board mandated elimination through attrition of virtually all firemen's positions in 1963. The ICRR's final response to its depressed situation was to merge with the Gulf, Mobile, and Ohio railroad in 1972 to form the Illinois Central Gulf Railroad. In 1998, the ICRR was purchased by the Canadian National Railway and integrated into its operations.
Scope and Contents
Inclusive date range: 1886-1973
Bulk dates: 1916-1968
Series 1: Historic Documents
Series 2: Subject Files
Series 3: Interpretation of Rules
Series 4: Railroad Case Files, Arbitrations, and supporting materials
Series 5: Miscellaneous
This collection contains select files from the Personnel Department of the Illinois Central Railroad [ICRR]. The records are arranged into five series which reflect the original file order the documents were housed in when still in use by their creators.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 5197: Illinois Central Gulf Railroad Miscellany 5188m: Association of American Railroads Agreement of May 1936 5943: Dan A. Ballard Collection of Railroad Memorabilia & Wage Information
Arrangement
Series 1: Historic Documents, 1886-1973
Series 2: Subject Files, 1901-1969
Series 3: Interpretation of Rules, 1911-1935
Series 4: Railroad Case Files, Arbitrations, and supporting materials, 1930-1971
Series 5: Miscellaneous, 1934-1954
Personnel management -- United States -- Sources; Railroads -- Illinois -- History; Railroads -- Buildings and structures -- Illinois; Railroads -- Employees; Wages -- Railroads -- United States; Industrial relations -- United States; Collective bargaining -- Railroads -- United States; Illinois Central Gulf Railroad Company; United States Railroad Administration; Yazoo and Mississippi Valley Railroad Company; Alabama and Vicksburg Railway; Vicksburg, Shreveport and Pacific Railroad; Paducah and Illinois Railroad Company; Missouri Pacific Railroad Company; Mississippi Central Railroad Company; Gulf and Ship Island Railroad Company
3119392
- Series 1: Historic Documents, 1886-1973
  Scope and Contents
  This series includes documents historically significant to the ICRR. There are records documenting a change in ICRR accounting practices and a booklet describing the development of the employee wage structure on railroads. An ICRR booklet from 1915 lists all employees of the ICRR at that time as well as including a complete roster of the company's engines and rolling stock and a map of the system. There are two pages of a Time Book from 1886 and a ticket from a train trip in 1891. There are also tickets from the last run of the Hawkeye train. Finally, this series contains the centenary address by ICRR president W.A. Johnston in a specially printed booklet that contains reproductions of photographs of the ICRR.
  - Historic development of the railroad wage structure, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 1b)
  - Changes in wages and working conditions of railway employees 1917-1924 (Box 1, Folder 1a)
  - Development of rates of pay of employees in seven major non-operating groups, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 1c)
  - Minutes of Conferences between ICRR and BLF&E, 1908-1934 (Box 1, Folder 2a)
  - ICRR Official list of officers, agents, attorneys, surgeons, stations, etc., 1915 (Box 1, Folder 2b)
    Includes entire roster of engines and rolling stock and map of system
  - Historical documents: Tickets, Claim Checks, Cash deposit Slips, 1886-1973 (Box 1, Folder 3a)
  - The Illinois Central Heritage, 1851-1951: A Centenary Address" by W. A. Johnston (Box 1, Folder 3b)
  - Historical rates of Pay: operating and Non-Operating, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 4a)
  - U.S. Railroad Administration: Agreement between Director General of railroads and the Brotherhood of Railway and Steamship Clerks, Freight Handlers, Express and Station Employees, 1920 (Box 1, Folder 4b)
- Series 2: Subject Files, 1901-1969
  This series is arranged alphabetically by subject (see folder list for all topics included). The records in this series consist of correspondence; transcripts of proceeding before arbitration and mediation boards; minutes of meetings; death records; documentation of disciplinary matters; employee claims forms; financial records, including extensive documentation of rates of pay, wage schedules, timekeeping, and vacation pay; newspaper and magazine clippings; government publications such as the Railway Labor Act and its subsequent amendments and other federal legislation impacting the ICRR; reproduced journal articles; pamphlets; decisions and circulars from the National Mediation Board; ICRR employee bulletins; results of union committee elections; railroad passes for employees; Red Scare Era propaganda publications; draft deferment forms; criminal trial proceedings; and records documenting the operations of the ICRR and its relations with the railroad labor organizations.
  In this series, there are records documenting ICRR's apprenticeship programs, including financial records, courses of study, correspondence with other carriers regarding their apprenticeship programs, and rosters of the names of the apprentices. There is also a sample apprenticeship certificate from 1955.
  This series includes extensive claims filings by ICRR employees. The claims, dating from 1935-1960, are arranged chronologically. They include the initial claim, correspondence, awards, decisions, transcripts, memoranda, and minutes of meetings regarding claims and grievances filed against the ICRR by its employees. The most prevalent issues include: seniority; safety; job description; facilities for training; lunch break; leaves of absence; overtime pay; assignments asking employees to work seven day in a row; work assignments; travelling expenses; starting time; pensions; physical examinations; theft of company property; wage discrepancies; and vacation time.
  The records of employee deaths, injuries, and illnesses from 1941-1946 are found in this series. In addition to the reports on the actual events, this file also includes correspondence regarding the nature of the incident as well as correspondence expressing well wishes from the ICRR to the injured employees and condolences to the surviving families of those employees who died. Disciplinary records, including investigations of alleged infractions, employee violations of the rules, and correspondence regarding the ways in which the infractions were documented in the employees' files are found in this series. Also of note is the extensive correspondence between the ICRR and other carriers regarding various disciplinary systems and the adoption of the Brown System, which uses a discipline by record approach.
  Of particular note are the discrimination files. They document the discrimination faced by the African-American employees of the ICRR. The discrimination files record the various efforts made by African-American employees to preserve their job security and seniority rights, particularly in the aftermath of the closed shop amendment to the Railway Labor Act. While the closed shop amendment was in theory designed to protect workers' rights, it had a staggeringly negative effect on African-American railroad men. The major railroad unions and brotherhoods only allowed white members, and once the closed shop amendment came into force, African-American employees were left unrepresented in all labor negotiations. In practice, this created a situation where the unions would use a form of "sharp practice," in which they would manipulate seniority rosters and local rules to keep African-Americans off the crew rosters so that initially they would lose jobs to white employees, and after six months they would lose their seniority and their jobs. The ICRR management was aware of the practice, and in internal communications recognized it as targeted discrimination, but declined to put a halt to it because the "sharp practice" was technically a legal application of the seniority rules. (See also Series 4 for lawsuits regarding seniority rules.) In response to these pressures, African-American railroad men attempted to organize themselves so that their interests would be protected. The correspondence between these early organizers and ICRR management are found in these files. Of note is the file dedicated to Thomas D. Redd, one of the co-founders of the Association of Colored Railway Trainmen and Locomotive Firemen (ACRT). The ACRT was founded in 1918, although the ICRR never recognized it and would only meet with Redd and the other representatives "as individuals." In 1934, the ACRT with other local chapters of African-American railroad men formed the International Association of Railway Employees (IARE). The ACRT/IARE and other local unions representing African-American employees also filed petitions before the Railroad Adjustment Board and when the Board refused, filed a Writ of Mandamus in an attempt to compel the Board to hear their grievances. The IARE joined the UTU in 1970. During its years of operation, the IARE fought to protect its members' seniority rights, protest discriminatory contracts, and protest the racialized violence that its members suffered at the hands of their white co-workers and the general public.
  Extensive documentation of the racialized violence African-American ICRR employees were subjected to are also found in these files. There were three periods of especially heightened racial violence in 1916, 1921-1922, and 1932-1933 when African-American trainmen were targeted by white gunman while doing their jobs. The discrimination files contain both an internal report from the ICRR detailing these atrocities. For the attacks in 1921-1922 and 1932-1933, the ICRR documented the names of all the men who were attacked, although they did not do so for the men who were attacked in 1916. The attackers in 1921-1922 are identified as members of the Klu Klux Klan, although no arrests were ever made. The attacks in 1933-1934 were carried out by four white ICRR employees and one other man not affiliated with the ICRR. These men were tried for their crimes. Three were convicted, and served minimal jail time. Two others, who were the first two arrested, and who identified their co-conspirators in sworn testimony, were both found not guilty by a jury. These two men then sued the ICRR for back pay, wrongful termination, and slander. The case file regarding these suits contains their confessions and portions of their criminal trials. The discrimination files also contain the reports of an ICRR Special Agent who summarized the events and the trial for ICRR management. Also found in these files are an internal report by the ICRR gathering data on these events and the report and notes the ICRR created for a federal investigation into workplace discrimination in 1934.
  The discrimination files are arranged alphabetically, however, due to outdated and offensive language, the folder titles have been updated to more suitable language (see processing note for further details).
  Files on jurisdictional disputes between non-operating shop crafts on specific task and the determinations by labor boards are found in this series. For additional information on the rules and interpretations that governed the work of non-operating shop craft employees, see series 3.
  Matters regarding wages, rates of pay, schedules, vacations and retirement funds determined by the Railroad Retirement Board are all located in this series. The files are organized by employee class and geographic division on the ICRR.
  Newspaper clippings documenting various strikes and threatened strikes in the 1960s during the crew consist disagreements between the carriers and unions are found in this file. For more information on this dispute, see Series 4 and the files containing the records regarding the lawsuits and arbitrations that arose from this issue. There are also clippings documenting strikes from other time periods, including the Freight Handlers' strike in 1902, the Clerks' strike of 1912, and the Longshoremen's strike in 1923. In addition to the clippings, there are many records documenting the ICRR management's attempts at union busting through the hiring of day laborers during the strikes of the Freight Handlers and the Clerks.
  The ICRR extensively documented the activities of its employees during World War 2. In additional to documenting their manpower concerns and their attempts to obtain draft deferrals for their skilled employees, the ICRR management also documented the service histories of all their employees who joined the armed forces. At the instigation of management, supervisors conducted brief interviews with all returning veterans, compiling brief accounts of each individuals experience in the war. These files contain a rich history of the service of thousands of railroad employees on the ICRR. The World War 2 files also contain information about how the company worked to find employment for returning veterans, to allow for leaves of absence so that veterans could take advantage of the G.I. Bill's various provisions, and what use the skills gained during service might be put to use in employment with the ICRR.
  Finally, in the post war period, the ICRR hosted numerous visitors in its various departments. The majority of these visitors were foreign nationals who were studying American railroad practices in order to apply them in their own countries. Representatives from places as diverse as Ghana, Japan, Italy, South Africa, Great Britain, France Australia, and India all spent time with various departments on the ICRR. Their visits are documented both through U.S. State Department records, but also through correspondence between ICRR management and the foreign representatives.
  - Accounting: Consolidation of Division, Shop and Storehouses [folder 1 of 2], 1930 (Box 1, Folder 5a)
    In addition to inter-office correspondence and financial forms, there are blueprints for proposed office and store house spaces
  - Accounting: Consolidation of Division, Shop and Storehouses [folder 2 of 2], 1930 (Box 1, Folder 5b)
  - Advertising, Institutional, 1941-1962 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    A run of the ICRR bulletin "Things to Talk About"
  - Agreements, General, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - American Economic System, Films regarding, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    List of films about ICRR and economy available
  - American Railway Supervisor's Association, Supervisory Employees, 1920-1941 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - America's Unknown War by John T. Flynn, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Red Scare Era speech, but file contains complete list of ICRR employees to whom copy of the speech was mailed by the personnel department
  - Apprenticeship, 1948-1951 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Correspondence with the Railway Education Bureau re apprenticeship programs at ICRR
  - Apprenticeship, 1952-1953 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Correspondence with Association of American Railroads to certify apprenticeship programs, with other railroads to arrange joint training programs, and with other railroads for examples of how to set up certain training programs
  - Apprenticeship, 1952-1955 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Invoices for training to Railway Education Bureau and progress reports on apprentices
  - Apprenticeship, 1952-1954 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    rosters of ICRR apprentices enrolled in various crafts
  - Apprenticeship, 1950-1955 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Correspondence with Railway Education Bureau, report from Texas and Pacific Railroad's apprenticeship program, a roster of ICRR apprentices, syllabi for apprenticeships, copy of Railway Age magazine with article on apprenticeships
  - ICRR Apprenticeship Certificate, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Arbitration of disputes between employees and carriers, general file, 1933-1953 (Box 1, Folder 17a)
  - Arbitration: National Mediation Board Circular No. 155 to 155-3, 1936-1937 (Box 1, Folder 17b)
    Arbitration between Western Pacific Railway, Tidewater Southern Railway, Sacramento Northern Railway and BLF&E, ORC
  - Assignment of Crews, operating department, 1921-1943 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Assignment of Crews, 1924-1942 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Association of Western Railways, National Mediation Board circulars, 1934-1938 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Association of American Railroads, Speakers' Manual, 1941-1945 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    Ordering of and list of ICRR personnel who have the manual
  - Baggage and Express Work, 1924-1935 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Baggage and Express Work - Runs, 1938 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Contain system canvas of classes of employees handling baggage and/or express
  - Chicago - Salaries paid for clerical occupations in, 1932 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Claims [folder 1 of 2], 1935 (Box 2, Folder 4a)
    Correspondence and minutes of meetings regarding employee grievances and claims
  - Claims [folder 2 of 2], 1935 (Box 2, Folder 4b)
  - Claims [folder 1 of 5], 1936 (Box 2, Folder 5a)
  - Claims [folder 2 of 5], 1936 (Box 2, Folder 5b)
  - Claims [folder 3 of 5], 1936 (Box 2, Folder 5c)
  - Claims [folder 3 of 5], 1936 (Box 2, Folder 5d)
  - Claims [folder 3 of 5], 1936 (Box 2, Folder 5e)
  - Claims [folder 1 of 7], 1937 (Box 2, Folder 6a)
  - Claims [folder 2 of 7], 1937 (Box 2, Folder 6b)
  - Claims [folder 3 of 7], 1937 (Box 2, Folder 6c)
  - Claims [folder 4 of 7], 1937 (Box 2, Folder 6d)
  - Claims [folder 5 of 7], 1937 (Box 2, Folder 6e)
  - Claims [folder 6 of 7], 1937 (Box 2, Folder 6f)
  - Claims [folder 7 of 7], 1937 (Box 2, Folder 6g)
  - Claims [folder 1 of 6], 1938-1939 (Box 3, Folder 1a)
  - Claims [folder 2 of 6], 1938-1939 (Box 3, Folder 1b)
  - Claims [folder 3 of 6], 1938-1939 (Box 3, Folder 1c)
  - Claims [folder 4 of 6], 1938-1939 (Box 3, Folder 1d)
  - Claims [folder 5 of 6], 1938-1939 (Box 3, Folder 1e)
  - Claims [folder 6 of 6], 1938-1939 (Box 3, Folder 1f)
  - Claims [folder 1 of 2], 1939 (Box 3, Folder 2a)
  - Claims [folder 2 of 2], 1939 (Box 3, Folder 2b)
  - Claims [folder 1 of 3], 1940 (Box 3, Folder 3a)
  - Claims [folder 2 of 3], 1940 (Box 3, Folder 3b)
  - Claims [folder 3 of 3], 1940 (Box 3, Folder 3c)
  - Claims [folder 1 of 3], 1941 (Box 3, Folder 4a)
  - Claims [folder 2 of 3], 1941 (Box 3, Folder 4b)
  - Claims [folder 3 of 3], 1941 (Box 3, Folder 4c)
  - Claims, 1942 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Claims [folder 1 of 4], 1943 (Box 4, Folder 1a)
  - Claims [folder 2 of 4], 1943 (Box 4, Folder 1b)
  - Claims [folder 3 of 4], 1943 (Box 4, Folder 1c)
  - Claims [folder 4 of 4], 1943 (Box 4, Folder 1d)
  - Claims [folder 1 of 2], 1944 (Box 4, Folder 2a)
  - Claims [folder 2 of 2], 1944 (Box 4, Folder 2b)
  - Claims [folder 1 of 3], 1945 (Box 4, Folder 3a)
  - Claims [folder 2 of 3], 1945 (Box 4, Folder 3b)
  - Claims [folder 3 of 3], 1945 (Box 4, Folder 3c)
  - Claims [folder 1 of 2], 1946 (Box 4, Folder 4a)
  - Claims [folder 2 of 2], 1946 (Box 4, Folder 4b)
  - Claims [folder 1 of 2], 1947 (Box 4, Folder 5a)
  - Claims [folder 2 of 2], 1947 (Box 4, Folder 5b)
  - Claims [folder 1 of 2], 1948 (Box 4, Folder 6a)
  - Claims [folder 2 of 2], 1948 (Box 4, Folder 6b)
  - Claims [folder 1 of 2], 1949 (Box 4, Folder 7a)
  - Claims [folder 2 of 2], 1949 (Box 4, Folder 7b)
  - Claims [folder 1 of 2], 1950 (Box 5, Folder 1a)
  - Claims [folder 1 of 2], 1951 (Box 5, Folder 2a)
  - Claims [folder 2 of 2], 1951 (Box 5, Folder 2b)
  - Claims [folder 1 of 2], 1952 (Box 5, Folder 3a)
  - Claims [folder 2 of 2], 1952 (Box 5, Folder 3b)
  - Claims [folder 1 of 2], 1953 (Box 5, Folder 4a)
  - Claims [folder 2 of 2], 1953 (Box 5, Folder 4b)
  - Claims [folder 1 of 7], 1954 (Box 5, Folder 5a)
  - Claims [folder 2 of 7], 1954 (Box 5, Folder 5b)
  - Claims [folder 3 of 7], 1954 (Box 5, Folder 5c)
  - Claims [folder 4 of 7], 1954 (Box 5, Folder 5d)
  - Claims [folder 5 of 7], 1954 (Box 5, Folder 5e)
  - Claims [folder 6 of 7], 1954 (Box 5, Folder 5f)
  - Claims [folder 7 of 7], 1954 (Box 5, Folder 5g)
  - Claims [folder 1 of 10], 1955-1956 (Box 6, Folder 1a)
  - Claims [folder 2 of 10], 1955-1956 (Box 6, Folder 1b)
  - Claims [folder 3 of 10], 1955-1956 (Box 6, Folder 1c)
  - Claims [folder 4 of 10], 1955-1956 (Box 6, Folder 1d)
  - Claims [folder 5 of 10], 1955-1956 (Box 6, Folder 1e)
  - Claims [folder 6 of 10], 1955-1956 (Box 6, Folder 1f)
  - Claims [folder 7 of 10], 1955-1956 (Box 6, Folder 1g)
  - Claims [folder 8 of 10], 1955-1956 (Box 6, Folder 1h)
  - Claims [folder 9 of 10], 1955-1956 (Box 6, Folder 1i)
  - Claims [folder 10 of 10], 1955-1956 (Box 6, Folder 1j)
  - Claims [folder 1 of 9], 1955-1956 (Box 6, Folder 2a)
  - Claims [folder 2 of 9], 1955-1956 (Box 6, Folder 2b)
  - Claims [folder 3 of 9], 1955-1956 (Box 6, Folder 2c)